Finding Aid for Flounders (Club) Records, 1935-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Flounders (Club) records, 1935-2003 1975-2003
Flounders (Club)
0.5 linear ft.
0446 Br 2
University of Michigan faculty water polo team. Administrative and background information; also photographs, videotape and DVD of Flounders events; and CD-ROMs of Flounders images and documents.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of Professor Richard Bailey (donor no. 5893 )
The record group is open to research.
Between 1925 and 1926 the University of Michigan swim coach Matt Mann started The Flounders, a water polo team for male faculty members. The members consistently met three times week, Monday, Wednesday, and Friday at noon at the Michigan Union pool, where they would play a quick game, then head off to a group lunch at the Union. The Flounders became known for their lack of definitive rules, rough playing style, and for not keeping an official score. When a member's name appeared in print that player was obligated to buy coffee or, as the updated rules state, ice-cream or both for the other members. Undergraduate students who were members of the swim team and sons of members were allowed to join the team, as long as they could make it through one game, which usually lasted half an hour and could involve being scratched, injured, or held under water for up to five minutes at a time.
The collection is comprised of two series; Administration and Background Information, and Other Media. The bulk of the records are in the Administration series, which contains information pertaining to the history of the organization, fundraising efforts by the Flounders for a score board, memorials, and bills for annual charges for supplies and rental of space. The Other Media series primarily documents random weekly games, team pictures, and the planting of a memorial tree in 1983 for deceased Flounder member John Slocum. There are also several CD-ROMS that contain images of members and miscellaneous clippings. A DVD is included that was created for the 75th anniversary of the founding of the Flounders in 2003. The paper records accumulated during the making of the anniversary DVD, which include typed captions for images, are within the administration series. A VHS Tape is also included as part of the collection that contains material documented in 2002.
Subjects:
Flounders (Club); University of Michigan--Faculty--Societies, etc.; Water polo--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Flounders (Club); Water polo--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; DVDs.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administration and Background Information, 1935-2003
  - Charges for Usage of the Intramural Sports Building (IMSB), 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising
    - General, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Hopkins, Clark Memorial Fund, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Scoreboard Fund, October 1992 (Box 1)
    - Slocum, John Memorial Tree, February 1993 (Box 1)
  - History, 1975-1994 (Box 1)
  - Images of Artwork dedicated to Eugene Power, January 1994 (Box 1)
  - The Making of the 75th Anniversary DVD, 2003, 2 floppy discs (Box 1)
  - Member Lists, 1976-1994 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - General, 1935-2002 (Box 1)
    - Slocum, John. Memorial Tree Dedication, May 1983 (Box 1)
- Other media
  - CD-ROMS
    - Christmas 2000 and Pool 2001 (Box 1)
    - Clippings and Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
    - Email Pictures and CB Scans, undated (Box 1)
    - June 1995-June 1997 (Box 1)
  - DVD
    - 75th Anniversary, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Negatives
    - Water polo Game, June 1975 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Slocum, John. Memorial Tree Dedication, May 1983 (Box 1)
    - Team Pictures, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Water polo Game, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Water polo Game, July 2000 (Box 1)
    - General, undated (Box 1)
  - VHS Videotape
    - "The Flounders, April 26, 2002" (Box 1)